Bromfield Street, Tremont Street, and People's Temple Methodist Church Records (Boston, Mass)
Bromfield Street, Tremont Street, and People's Temple Methodist Church Records (Boston, Mass)
1856-1922
1 linear ft.
Partial records for three Boston-area Methodist Episcopal churches: Tremont Street (1862-1913), People's Temple (1879-1922), and Bromfield Street (1806-1913). Tremont and Bromfield merged in 1913 to become Bromfield-Tremont (1913-1922), and both merged with People's Temple in 1922 to form The United Church (1922-1925).
2575979
Biographical History
The Bromfield Street church (1806-1913) began in 1806 as a branch of the Methodist Alley (First) church. It became independent in 1831, at which time it was listed as Boston South, and became Bromfield Street Church in 1835. Black congregants were given their own local pastor, Samuel Snowdon, in 1818 and their own church on May Street in 1823, under the sponsorship of Bromfield. Bromfield took the corporate name of Methodist Religious Society in Boston in 1870, and in 1911 or 1913 its congregation merged with Tremont Street to form Bromfield-Tremont.
Tremont Street church (1862-1913) began as Suffolk Street Methodist Episcopal Church, became Hedding Chapel in 1852, and Tremont Street in 1862. Tremont Street became a major congregation; the Woman's Foreign Missionary Society was founded there in 1869, and memorial windows for this organization are found throughout the church.
The People's Temple (1879-1922) was founded by Bishop John W. Hamilton as a continuation of the Church Street M.E. Church, and moved in 1884 to the corner of Columbus Avenue and Berkeley Street. Forty years later, in 1922, the congregation merged with Bromfield-Tremont to form The United Church, which continued to meet at the Tremont location.
[Sources: New England Conference of the United Methodist Church Commission on Archives and History.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bromfield Street, Tremont Street, and People's Temple Methodist Church Records (Boston, Mass) contain partial records for three related Boston-area Methodist Episcopal churches. The Bromfield Street material consists of a memorial register of probationers and offerings, and records of trustee cash accounts. The Tremont Street material includes treasurer's reports, lists of members and pew deeds, Sunday school records, and two items from the Secretary of the Women's Foreign Missionary Society. The People's Temple material consists entirely of items relating to the Women's Foreign Missionary Society.
Related Material
has collections relating to a number of churches and the papers of several clergymen and ministers, particularly Unitarian Universalist. Please refer to the for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Bromfield Street Methodist Episcopal Church.; Bromfield-Tremont Street Methodist Episcopal Church.; Methodist Episcopal Church -- History.; Methodist Episcopal Church. -- Woman's Foreign Missionary Society.; People's Temple Methodist Episcopal Church.; Tremont Street Methodist Episcopal Church.; Churches -- Massachusetts -- Boston.; Account books.; Church records.; Registers.; Reports.; Church secretaries.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Donated along with the First Methodist Church Syracuse Records. Removed to form separate collection, Nov 2007.
Inventory
- Tremont Street
  - Church treasurer's account book, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Church treasurer's record book, 1900?; 1903-1904,; 1909,; 1910,; undated (Box 1)
  - List of members and cash account, 1896-1903; 1888-1896,; 1916-1922,; 1904-1916,; 1917 (Box 1)
  - Pew deeds, 1870s (Box 1)
  - Sunday School records, 1908-1917 (Box 1)
  - Trustee cash accounts, 1856-1876 (Box 1)
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society recording secretary's book, 1887-1902 (Box 1)
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society secretary's reports, 1887-1899; 1899-1912,; 1913-1922 (Box 1)
- Bromfield Street
  - Memorial register of probationers and thank offerings, 1899-1901 (Box 1)
  - Trustee cash accounts, 1886-1891 (Box 1)
- People's Temple
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society recording secretary's book, 1912-1922 (Box 1)
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society treasurer's book, 1920-1922 (Box 1)
  - Woman's Home Missionary Society treasurer's book, 1890-1922 (Box 1)